Finding Aid for Louis William Doll papers, 1937-1951
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Louis William Doll papers 1937-1951
Doll, Louis Wm. (Louis William), 1911-
85146 Aa 2; UAl
Bay City, Michigan, librarian, historian, and teacher; archivist of the Historical Division of the Far East Command in Japan after World War II. Diaries describing life and activities in Japan; letters from friends and family during and after the Second World War; doctoral thesis and miscellanea; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
8 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The collection was the gift of Louis Doll (donor no. 1338 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Louis W. Doll was born in Chelsea, Michigan in 1911, later moving to Ann Arbor in 1922. He received degrees in history and library science from the University of Michigan. He entered the army in 1942 and served five years with the Japanese Language School. After the war, he was appointed archivist of the Historical Division of the Far East Command in Japan. He moved to Bay City in 1953 becoming a professor of history at Delta College. He retired in 1977. In addition to teaching, Doll also wrote books and articles about local Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County history. He died September 25, 2001.
The collection consists primarily of diaries and correspondence from the period when Doll served in Japan.
Subjects:
Doll, Louis Wm. (Louis William), 1911-; East Asia.; Japan.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Railroad bridges.; Bicycles and tricycles.; Boats.; Doll, Louis Wm. (Louis William), 1911-; Lower Town (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Offices--1891-1900.; Postal Telegraph-Cable Company (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Railroad bridges--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Telegraph.; Whitmore Lake (Mich.); World War, 1939-1945.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Diaries / writings
  - Essay: "Higher education in a democracy" from Neo-practical English series for neo-Japanese (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    - January 24-September 14, 1946 (Box 1)
    - September 14, 1946-May 12, 1947 (Box 1)
    - December 7, 1947-December 7, 1948 (Box 1)
    - December 8, 1948-December 7, 1949 (Box 1)
    - December 8, 1949-July 25, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Doctoral thesis: "Secular Aspects of the English Episcopate During the Reigns of Henry III and Edward 1, 1216-1307" University of Michigan 1937 (Box 1)
  - Japanese surrender leaflets and miscellanea (Box 1)
- Correspondence and other papers 1941-1951
  - Acampora, Tullius (Box 2)
  - Adachi family (Box 2)
  - Akita, Taro (Box 2)
  - Andrews, Lawrence K. (Box 2)
  - Aoki, Teruo (Box 2)
  - Arlt, Mary (Box 2)
  - Arlt, Richard (Box 2)
  - Aurelius, Sister Mary (Box 2)
  - Balsly, R.T. (Box 2)
  - Baxter, Pearle O. (Box 2)
  - Beissel, Leonard (Box 2)
  - Bengal, Josephine (Box 2)
  - Berridge, W. Lloyd (Box 2)
  - Bishop, William W. (Box 2)
  - Bowler, Inez (Box 2)
  - Branson, Ann (Box 2)
  - Brigham, Alice (Box 2)
  - Brigham, George (Box 2)
  - Brigham, Ilma (Box 2)
  - Cora C. (Box 2)
  - Carbone, John (Box 2)
  - Caspary (Frances and William) (Box 2)
  - Cavinee, Henry (Box 2)
  - Chiba, Luke D. (Box 2)
  - Cook, Ron (Box 2)
  - Cortese, Michael (Box 2)
  - Craft, Howard D. (Box 2)
  - Crandall, Fred and Olive (Box 2)
  - Cunningham, William. E. (Box 2)
  - Davis, Raymond C. (Box 2)
  - Doll, Anna Mary (Beissel) (Box 2)
  - Doll, Anna Mary (Beissel) (Box 3)
  - Doll, E. Elaine (Ewing) (Box 3)
  - Doll, Frederick L. (Box 3)
  - Doll, James V. (Box 3)
  - Doll, John Edward (Box 3)
  - Doll, Louis William
    - October 16, 1940-September 26, 1943 (Box 4)
    - October 1, 1943-May 20, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Doll, Marjorie Mott (Box 6)
  - Doll, Maurice F. (Box 6)
  - Doll, William Henry (Box 6)
  - Dombrowski, John F. (Box 6)
  - Donegan, Dorcas (Box 6)
  - Donegan, Marie (Box 6)
  - Ebizuka, Atsuo (Box 6)
  - Edwardine, Sister Mary (Box 6)
  - Endo (Box 6)
  - Ewen, Ross F. (Box 6)
  - Fifield, Tom (Box 6)
  - Folsom, H.K. (Box 6)
  - Fred (friend of Doll's) (Box 6)
  - Fukuda, Naomi (Box 6)
  - Gill, Florence T. (Box 7)
  - Gillies, Tom (Box 7)
  - Gjelsness, Rudolph (Box 7)
  - Halker, Frances E. (Box 7)
  - Halstead, William P. (Box 7)
  - Haneyama, Kazuo (Box 7)
  - Hatchman, Norman G. (Box 7)
  - Henderson, Mabel (Box 7)
  - Higuchi, Masakazu (Box 7)
  - Higuchi, Masao (Box 7)
  - Hinamoto, Hirohide (Box 7)
  - Hindelang, Agnes Bertille (Box 7)
  - Hindelang, Margaret (Doll) (Box 7)
  - Hindelang, Odo A. (Box 7)
  - Hobbs, Sam (Box 7)
  - Hogan, Rev. Steve (Box 7)
  - Hughes, Herbert (Box 7)
  - Hundt, Katherine (Stapish) (Box 7)
  - Igaki, Haruo (Box 7)
  - Inomata, Takeshi (Box 7)
  - Jansen, Jacob E. (Box 7)
  - Jimenez, B. (Box 7)
  - Johnson, Rev. Peter Leo (Box 7)
  - Jones, Bernard M. (Box 7)
  - Jones, Kenneth L. (Box 7)
  - Jones, Roland (Box 7)
  - Kamikawa, H. (Box 7)
  - Kane, D.G. (Box 7)
  - Kawaii, Hiroshi (Box 7)
  - Keedle, Hazel (Box 7)
  - Keusch, Ida (Box 7)
  - Keusch, John P. (Box 7)
  - Kistler, Charles (Box 7)
  - Kranach, Ernest E. (Box 7)
  - Kobayashi Yutaka (Box 7)
  - Kujiraoka, Sozaburo (Box 7)
  - Lally, Mary Elizabeth (Box 7)
  - Lautenschlager, Ava (Box 7)
  - Leeder, Jacob (Box 7)
  - Lindquist, Peter Carl (Box 7)
  - Lohman, Louise (Box 7)
  - McAllister, Samuel W. (Box 7)
  - McAvoy, Thomas T. (Box 7)
  - McCudden, Mr. and Mrs. Frank (Box 7)
  - Machida, Cecilia Toshiko (Box 7)
  - Maginn, Gertrude (Box 7)
  - Matsuo, T. (Box 7)
  - Matsuo, Yoshiko (Box 7)
  - Maulbetch, William C. (Box 7)
  - Merkel, Monica (Box 7)
  - Miller, Helen (Box 7)
  - Miwa, Sukemichi (Box 7)
  - Miwa, Takehisa (Box 7)
  - Mizuno, Kenichi (Box 7)
  - Moote, Paul A. (Box 7)
  - Moote, Silas V. (Box 7)
  - Mori, Kiyoshi (Box 7)
  - Morrill, Clarence (Box 8)
  - Morrill, Dorothea (Box 8)
  - Mortiboy, Alice (Box 8)
  - Mott, Blanche (Box 8)
  - Mouw, Gerritt E. (Box 8)
  - Nagasaka, Shoichi (Box 8)
  - Nager, Kalman O. (Box 8)
  - Nakagawa, James (Box 8)
  - Nakamura, Michiaki (Box 8)
  - Nixon, Mrs. Nathan L. (Box 8)
  - Oakes, Ray E. (Box 8)
  - Okada, Naro (Box 8)
  - Otti, Lt. R.L. (Box 8)
  - Palmer, Bob (Box 8)
  - Paradise, Bob F. (Box 8)
  - Paris, John W. (Box 8)
  - Parsons, Bess (Box 8)
  - Peek, Rev. G. Warren (Box 8)
  - Powell, Donald M. (Box 8)
  - Price, Arnold H. (Box 8)
  - Quirk, Dr. Edmund J. (Box 8)
  - Quirk, Helen (Brown) (Box 8)
  - Ransom, Dale (Box 8)
  - Rasmussen, Kai E. (Box 8)
  - Reynak, Thomas (Box 8)
  - Riggs, Marie (Box 8)
  - Rose Vincent, Sister M. (Box 8)
  - Rosenfeld, Dorothy (Box 8)
  - Reuter, Mr. and Mrs. Neal (Box 8)
  - Runey, Joseph B. (Box 8)
  - Rush, Paul F. (Box 8)
  - Saiber, Jacob (Box 8)
  - Saito, Akira (Box 8)
  - Saito, Hajime (Box 8)
  - Saito, Kinichi (Box 8)
  - Saito, Satoshi (Box 8)
  - Sasaki, Yoshichika (Box 8)
  - Sato, Rev. Cyprian Mitsuyuki (Box 8)
  - Savaignac, Rev. V.G. (Box 8)
  - Shepherd, Richard J. (Box 8)
  - Shidachi, Peter Takauji (Box 8)
  - Shidachi, Yasushi (Box 8)
  - Simpson, Patrick Guy (Box 8)
  - Skarshaug, Pauline Waite (Box 8)
  - Smithe, Geneva (Box 8)
  - Stewart, Dorothy (Box 8)
  - Suetake, H. (Box 8)
  - Suzuki, Mieko (Box 8)
  - Suzuki, Noboru (Box 8)
  - Suzuki, Takeshi (Box 8)
  - Suzuki, Yukihisa (Box 8)
  - Swindler, Henry O. (Box 8)
  - Tajika, Taiichi (Box 8)
  - Takanobu, Kyosui (Box 8)
  - Tanabe, Kiyoko (Box 8)
  - Taylor, Vincent J. (Box 8)
  - Tomifuji, Sueko (Box 8)
  - Tonougar, Mary A. (Box 8)
  - Tsuchida family (Box 8)
  - Uhler, Katherine (Box 8)
  - Ullmann, Fred (Box 8)
  - Usami, Tokue (Box 8)
  - Watanabe family (Box 8)
  - Watanabe, Akiko (Box 8)
  - Watanabe, Hisako (Box 8)
  - Watanabe, Paul O. (Box 8)
  - Watkins, Herbert G. (Box 8)
  - Webster, Randolph E. (Box 8)
  - Wedemeyer, Josephine (Box 8)
  - Wirkner, Rose (Doll) (Box 8)
  - Yadaka, Tsuguo (Box 8)
  - Yamazaki, Atsuo (Box 8)
  - Yasui, Hisayoshi (Box 8)
  - Yedele, Florence and Frank (Box 8)
  - Yoder, Dr. O.R. (Box 8)
  - Zollman, W.B. (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Election of 1936 campaign literature (Box 8)
  - Historical sketches of St. Joseph Mercy Hospital and Mercywood (the clinic of St. Joseph's Sanitarium) (Box 8)
  - Volume: 1942 Artillery School, Camp Davis, North Carolina (Box 8)
  - Photographs (Box 8)
  - Photographs of Camp Davis, North Carolina (Folder UAm)